Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub Made possible with a grant from the Leon Levy Foundation 2009-2011 MSS 309
© 2010 Fales Library and Special Collections
- Irene Sax
  Beard, James, 1903-1985; Cofacci, Gino; Cunningham, Marion; Disney.com.; Epicurious.; Food Arts.; Gourmet.; Jones, Judith, 1924-; Kafka, Barbara; Martha Stewart Living.; New York Daily News.; Newsday.; Sax, Irene; Wilson, José; Authors and publishers.; Cooking |v Periodicals; Editing; Food writing.; Freelance writing; Ghostwriting; Manuscripts |x Editing
  - Interview 1, April 29, 2009
    Running time: 35 minutes
- Reese Schonfeld
  The Food Network has arguably had the greatest impact on the way Americans think about food. The network was launched in November 1993 as TVFN with 6.8 million cable subscribers. Scripps, the Food Network's parent company, has started its own magazine based on the popularity of food programs and advertiser demand. In May 2010, Scripps initiated a second 24-hour network of food programming called The Cooking Channel.
  It was Reese Schonfeld who got the Food Network going, developing the concept with a group put together by the Providence Journal Company's president Trygve Myhren. Schonfeld was a natural for the job. A longtime TV journalist and entrepreneur, he'd been the first president and chief executive of another big television success story, CNN, which he co-founded with Ted Turner in 1979.
  This interview tracks his early life, education, and career. Schonfeld also speaks about the early years of cable television and his participation in it, the original programming concepts and stars at TVFN, and the way the network redefined the image of food and cooking in American homes.
  Field, Sally
  Flay, Bobby
  Hanover, Donna, 1950-
  Lagasse, Emeril
  Leach, Robin
  Myhren, Tryg
  Ray, Rachael
  Rosengarten, David
  Schonfeld, Reese
  Turner, Ted
  Belo Broadcasting
  Cable News Network
  Food Channel
  Food Network (Firm)
  Independent Television News Association
  Iron chef (Television program)
  Johnson & Wales University. College of Culinary Arts
  Providence Journal Company
  United Press International
  Cable television
  Cooking -- United States
  Digital television
  Direct broadcast satellite television
  Food habits -- United States
  Batali, Mario; Belo Broadcasting.; British Broadcasting Corporation.; Cable News Network.; Child, Julia; Cunningham, Marion; Field, Sally; Flay, Bobby; Food Channel.; Food Network (Firm).; Hanover, Donna, 1950-; Independent Television News Association.; Iron chef (Television program).; Jognson & Wales University. College of Culinary Arts.; Lagasse, Emeril; Leach, Robin; Myhren, Tryg; Providence Journal Company.; Ray, Rachael; Rosengarten, David; Schonfeld, Reese; Turner, Ted; United Press International.; Cable television; Cooking |z United States; Digital television; Direct broadcast satellite television; Food habits |z United States; Television cooking shows
  - Interview 1, August 18, 2009
- Gus Schumacher
  High-level government employees are rarely known for sharing information with outsiders. It can be particularly difficult to get answers to questions about agricultural economics or the American food system. Yet Gus Schumacher—the only farmer in the Harvard class of 1961—has always considered educating the public (and the U.S. Congress) an essential and enjoyable part of his role.
  As Commissioner of Agriculture of Massachusetts, Administrator of the Foreign Agriculture Service, and then Undersecretary of the Farm and Foreign Agriculture Service at the USDA in the Clinton administration, Schumacher consistently found ways to spread the word. He educated reporters; regularly spoke on the farm radio network; facilitated conversations between journalists, political officials, farmers, and agricultural economists; and was always available to explain a new law or regulation or Farm Bill.
  Since he left government in 2007, Schumacher has continued that pattern as a consultant. Assisting and enabling new farmers—immigrants, women, young people—is one of his passions. Currently Schumacher is also the president of Wholesome Wave, a Connecticut-based charitable foundation that has been particularly active in finding ways to help the needy purchase nutritionally-rich produce at farmers markets at discount rates.
  All of these subjects are discussed in these interviews.
  Clinton, Bill, 1946-
  Dukakis, Michael S. (Michael Stanley), 1933-
  Espy, Mike, 1953-
  Hamersley, Gordon
  McNamara, Robert S., 1916-2009
  Newman, Paul, 1925-2008
  Nischan, Michel
  Waterston, Albert
  Winthrop, Freddie
  Commodity Credit Corporation
  HeartBeat Restaurant
  Massachusetts. Commission on Agriculture
  New American Farmer Initiative
  People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals
  United States. Food and Nutrition Service
  World Bank
  Farmers’ markets -- Massachusetts
  Farmers’ markets -- New York (State) -- New York
  Refugees -- United States
  Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children (U.S.)
  Tomatoes
  Batterberry, Michael; Benepe, Barry; Child, Julia; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Commodity Credit Corporation.; Dukakis, Michael S., (Michael Stanley), 1933-; Espy, Mike, 1953-; Food Network (Firm).; Greenmarket.; Hamersley, Gordon; HeartBeat Restaurant.; Kellogg Foundation.; Lewis, Bob; Massachusetts. Commission on Agriculture.; McNamara, Robert S., 1916-2009; McPhee, John, 1931-; Monsanto Agricultural Company.; New American Farmer Initiative.; Newman, Paul, 1925-2008; Nischan, Michel; People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals.; Schumacher, Gus; United States. Department of Agriculture.; United States. Food and Nutrition Service.; Waterston, Albert; Wholesome Wave Foundation.; Winthrop, Freddie; World Bank.; Agricultural processing industries; Agriculture and state; Animal rights; Community -supported agriculture; Farm produce; Farmer's markets |z Massachusetts; Farmer's markets |z New York (State) |z New York; Food habits |z United States; Food industry and trade; Food stamps; Local foods; Nutrition; Produce trade; Refugees |z United States; Special Supplemental Nutrition Program for Women, Infants, and Children (U.S.); Tomatoes; Union Square (New York, N.Y.)
  - Interview 1, June 4, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 34 minutes
  - Interview 2, October 6, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 16 minutes
- Mimi Sheraton
  Mimi Sheraton is a writer, critic, and cookbook author perhaps best known for her transformational work as a restaurant critic at The New York Times from 1975 to 1984. She has worked at Good Housekeeping, Seventeen, House Beautiful, and Time and written for The New Yorker, Vogue, Smithsonian Magazine, and Smart Money.
  Brown, Helen Gurley
  Sheraton, Mimi
  Snyder, Jerome
  White, Agnes
  Condé Nast’s Traveler
  Cosmopolitan
  Cue New York
  Gault Millau (Firm)
  Guide du Pneu Michelin
  House Beautiful
  New York
  Seventeen
  Time
  Cooking, American -- History --20th century
  Local food
  Baum, Joseph; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Brown, Helen Gurley; Claiborne, Craig; Condé Nast's Traveler.; Cosmopolitan.; Cue New York.; Four Seasons (Restaurant).; Gault Millau (Firm).; Glaser, Milton; Gourmet.; Guide du Pneu Michelin.; House Beautiful.; New York Times.; New York.; Pavillon (Restaurant: New York, N.Y.).; Restaurant Associates.; Seventeen.; Sheraton, Mimi; Snyder, Jerome; Time.; White, Agnes; Authorship; Cooking |v Periodicals; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Dinners and dining; Food habits |z United States; Food industry and trade; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Journalism.; Local foods; Produce trade; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, July 2, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 17 minutes
  - Interview 2, July 20, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 26 minutes
- Michael Whiteman
  One of the most ubiquitous eating venues today is the food court—an essential component in suburban shopping malls, office complexes, railroad stations, and other public spaces. Upscale versions are currently very fashionable in New York City. We take them for granted.
  But food courts run by a single operator didn't exist until the 1970s, when restaurant consultants Joe Baum and Michael Whiteman created The Big Kitchen, a 350-seat complex on the concourse level of the World Trade Center.
  Baum, who was the president of Restaurant Associates (RA) for many years, was a life force in the restaurant industry, a man full of innovative methods of preparing and serving food at places like The Four Seasons, The Forum of the Twelve Caesars, and Fonda del Sol. In 1970, Baum left RA to form his own consulting company. In that same year, he landed a big contract to create the master plan for restaurants in the World Trade Center, and he needed help.
  His choice was the much younger Whiteman, then the Editor of Nation's Restaurant News, a biweekly trade magazine he had created. Eventually the two set up "Baum + Whiteman - The World's Preeiminent Food + Restaurant Consulting Company." After Baum's death in 1998, Whiteman and his wife, chef and cookbook author Rozanne Gold, carried on the business with Dennis Sweeney.
  Whiteman discusses that history and the company's work since then. He includes memories of working with James Beard, one of of the consultants on the World Trade Center restaurant project.
  Gold, Rosanne, 1954-
  Kumin, Albert
  Lang, George, 1924-
  Whiteman, Michael
  Wines, Barry
  Hilton International (Firm)
  National Gallery of Art (U.S.)
  Port Authority of New York and New Jersey
  Quilted Giraffe (Restaurant)
  Rainbow Room (Restaurant)
  Stars (Restaurant)
  Baum, Joseph; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Four Seasons (Restaurant).; Glaser, Milton; Gold, Rosanne, 1954-; Hilton International (Firm).; Kafka, Barbara; Kumin, Albert; Lang, George, 1924-; National Gallery of Art (U.S.).; Port Authority of New York and New Jersey.; Pépin, Jacques; Quilted Giraffe (Restaurant).; Rainbow Room (Restaurant).; Restaurant Associates.; Stars (Restaurant).; Tower, Jeremiah; Whiteman, Michael; Windows on the World (New York, N.Y.).; Wine, Barry; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.).; Cookery, American |x History |y 20th century.; Food habits |z United States; Food industry and trade |z United States.; Food service; Restaurant management; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, September 21, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 30 minutes
- Jane White Viazzi
  An actress and cabaret performer in the late 1940s and 1950s, Jane White Viazzi was married to Alfredo Viazzi, owner of several Greenwich Village restaurants that featured Italian regional cooking before it was fashionable. The daughter of Walter White, the executive director of the NAACP from 1931-1955, and Gladys White, Viazzi grew up amid the optimism and pride of the Harlem Renaissance.
  In this interview she discusses her childhood; her education at the Ethical Culture Schools in New York City and Smith College; her career; her husband's groundbreaking restaurants; and their friendship with James Beard.
  Bauer, Jerry
  Epstein, Jason
  Gussow, Ann
  Mann, Ted
  Viazzi, Alfredo
  White, Jane
  White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955
  Circle in the Square (Theater)
  National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
  Civil rights movements -- United States
  Harlem Renaissance
  Bauer, Jerry; Baum, Joseph; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Circle in the Square (Theater).; Epstein, Jason; Gussow, Ann; Mann, Ted; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Viazzi, Alfredo; White, Jane; White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955; Acting.; Civil rights movement |z United States; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Cooking, Italian; Gastronomy.; Harlem Renaissance; Restaurant management; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, March 25, 2009
- Clark Wolf
  A food and hospitality consultant, Clark Wolf has advised a wide range of clients including restaurants, hotels, casinos, public institutions, and specialty food companies. Wolf was a far-sighted cheese purveyor in San Francisco when James Beard walked into his cheese shop one day. The meeting launched a friendship that lasted from the early 1980s until Beard's death in 1985. Encouraged by Beard to come to New York, Wolf made the move in 1982 when Barbara Kafka invited him to open her specialty shop, Star Spangled Foods. Although he kept a home in Northern California, Wolf has maintained a New York presence ever since. An enthusiastic supporter of and fundraiser for New York University's Food Studies program, Wolf created the popular Critical Topics series on food studies for the Fales Library. He is the author of the 2008 American Cheeses.
  These interviews track his early years, his life in San Francisco, his first meeting with James Beard, his arrival in New York, his work as a food and restaurant consultant, and his longtime friendship with Beard.
  Carroll, John
  Gilder, Emily
  Grimes, William
  Mariani, John F.
  Phelps, Joseph
  Reichl, Ruth
  Rogers, Judy
  Santo, Joseph
  Spector, Stephen
  Tower Jeremiah
  American Cheese Society
  Arizona 266 (Restaurant)
  Cook’s Magazine
  Loews Hotels
  Markham (Restaurant)
  Oakville Grocery
  Sign of the Dove (Restaurant)
  Yellowfingers (Restaurant)
  Cheese
  Cooking, American -- California style
  Restaurants -- California -- San Francisco
  American Cheese Society.; American Institute of Wine & Food.; Arizona 266 (Restaurant).; Baum, Joseph; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Bloomingdale's (Firm).; Burros, Marian Fox; Carroll, John; Cofacci, Gino; Cook's Magazine.; Cunningham, Marion; Gilder, Emily; Glaser, Milton; Grimes, William; Kafka, Barbara; Kump, Peter; Leows Hotels.; Lewis, Bob; Mariani, John F.; Markham (Restaurant).; Nestle, Marion; New York University.; Oakville Grocery.; Phelps, Joseph; Reichl, Ruth; Rogers, Judy; Santo, Joseph; Sign of the Dove (Restaurant).; Spector, Stephen; Taylor, Marvin J.; Tower, Jeremiah; Waters, Alice; Wolf, Clark; Yellowfingers (Restaurant).; Cheese; Cooking |x Study and teaching; Cooking, American |x California Style; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Food habits; Food industry and trade |z United States.; Food service; Gastronomy.; Homosexuality; Restaurant management; Restaurants |z California |z San Francisco; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Interview 1, June 15, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 24 minutes
  - Interview 2, July 7, 2010
    Running time: 1 hour, 47 minutes
- Nina Zagat
  Nina Zagat is the co-founder and co-chair of the Zagat Survey. Along with her husband, she oversees the company's global operations and expansion, including its entry into new US and international markets, leisure categories and content platforms, and web and wireless ventures.
  Nina earned an LLB from Yale Law School in 1966 and an AB from Vassar College in 1963. Following law school, she spent 24 years as an attorney at the Wall Street law firm of Shearman and Sterling. When their firms sent the couple to Paris, Nina Zagat attended Le Cordon Bleu cooking school. Nina Zagat was named one of the Leading Women Entrepreneurs of the World by the Star Group in 2001, one of Crain's Top Tech 100, which featured New York City's most influential people in technology in 2001, and one of Crain New York's 100 Most Influential Women in 2007.
  Zagat, Nina
  Zagat, Tim
  Cordon bleu (School: Paris, France)
  Enu Ti Ti Dokomo (Firm)
  Sherman & Sterling
  Zagat Survey (Firm)
  Booksellers and bookselling
  Guidebooks
  Paris (France) -- History -- 20th century
  Social media
  User-generated content
  Claiborne, Craig; Cordon bleu (School: Paris, France).; Enu Ti Ti Dokomo (Firm).; Sherman & Sterling.; Zagat Survey (Firm).; Zagat, Nina; Zagat, Tim; Booksellers and bookselling; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Electronic publishing; Food habits; Food industry and trade; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Guidebooks; Paris (France) |x History |y 20th century; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants; Restaurants |z France |z Paris; Social media; User-generated content
  - Interview 1, December 23, 2009
    Running time: 1 hour, 31 minutes
- Tim Zagat
  Born on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, where he and his wife Nina still live, Tim Zagat grew up in a home where food wasn't a particular focus. His mother's only food passion involved freezing foods—both before or after cooking. Her freezing habit was so strong that marked and dated packages retrieved from her freezer much later on could be identified as the 1955 Thanksgiving turkey or the 1957 Easter ham. The food Tim Zagat ate at school wasn't much better. "Chicken a la King was a high point," he recalls. But his father and grandfather, who liked fine dining, set the stage for the future by taking the young man to some of the best restaurants of the 50s.
  After a few post-college years when he considered a life of poltics and public service, Tim Zagat went to Yale Law School. There his home-cooked culinary world opened up when he met and married classmate, and good cook, Nina Safronoff.
  Moyers, Bill D.
  Myhrvold, Nathan
  Shriver, Sargent, 1915 -
  Facebook (Firm)
  Hughes Hubbard & Reed
  Peace Corps (U.S.)
  Twitter (Firm)
  United States National Student Association
  User- generated content
  Facebook (Firm).; Hughes Hubbard & Reed.; Moyers, Bill D.; Myhrvold, Nathan; Peace Corps (U.S.).; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-; Twitter (Firm).; United States National Student Association.; Zagat Survey (Firm).; Zagat, Nina; Zagat, Tim; Booksellers and bookselling; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th Century; Electronic publishing; Food habits; Food industry and trade; Food writing.; Gastronomy.; Guidebooks; Publishers and publishing; Restaurants; Social media; User-generated content; Wine
  - Interview 1, December 3, 2009